ORIGINAL STORY BY NATSU HYUUGA
（原作：日向夏）
THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、组织名均为虚构 与任何特定事件或现象无关）
Maomao.
猫猫
Can you deliver medicine to the Verdigris House?
你可以把药送去绿青馆吗？
Got it, old man.
好的 老爹
A lot of women are getting kidnapped recently.
最近有很多女性被绑架
Be careful.
你要小心
I'll be fine.
我没事的啦
I'll stop by the farm.
我会顺便去农场
All right. Thank you.
好 麻烦你了
I'm off!
我走咯
THE VERDIGRIS HOUSE
（绿青馆）
That's all you've got?
你就只有这些？
Come on, this is my whole fortune!
那是我所有的财产 帮帮忙吧
Out of the question.
门都没有
That's one of the Verdigris House's prized Three Princesses,
那可是声名远播的绿青馆三美人当中
the popular Pairin!
最受欢迎的白铃
Don't look without paying!
没付钱不准看
It's not healing fast enough. I'll change the recipe.
痊愈的速度不够快 我来改变药方
Oh, Maomao.
猫猫
Big Sis Pairin!
白铃姐姐
Look at those new scars!
你又弄出新伤疤了！
Oh, this?
这个？
They're experiments for my medicine, like usual.
那只是为了药方做的实验啦 就跟平常一样
Are you eating properly?
你有乖乖吃饭吗？
Those things are impressive as always.
大姐还是如往常一样波涛“胸”涌
Maomao! If one of your little experiments
猫猫 如果你的小实验又不小心
blows up this room, I won't forgive you!
炸毁了这个房间 我可饶不了你
Or would you rather work as a courtesan here instead?
还是你想成为这儿的娼妓？
Shoot!
呃！
Granny, I'm leaving the medicine here!
奶奶 我把药给留在这儿咯
Say hello to the old man for me!
代我向老头子问好
Geez.
真是的
I heard Maomao's voice.
我听到猫猫的声音了
-Where did Maomao go? -She ran away.
-咦？猫猫人呢？ -她逃跑了
That sleazy granny…
那个低级的老鸨…
She tells me to be a courtesan any chance she gets!
一有机会就叫我当娼妓
Could they be kidnappers?
难道他们就是绑匪吗？
Old man will worry about me.
老爹会担心我的
The Eastern Palace heir is born!
东宫储君诞生了
Congratulations, Lady Lihua!
恭喜你 梨花娘娘
Her baby was delivered without issues.
她生产的过程很顺利
I see. I'm glad…
这样啊 太好了…
THREE MONTHS LATER
（三个月后）
I want to eat skewers from the market…
好想吃市场的烤肉串…
I hope the old man is eating properly.
老爹有没有好好吃饭啊？
So annoying. I don't know if I was sold off or used as a scapegoat,
烦死了 也不知道是被卖掉了 还是被用来当做替死鬼
but it's been three months since I got here.
自那时起已经三个月了
The palace and the pleasure district are not that different.
宫里跟花街其实没什么不一样
I wanted to avoid getting involved in the rear palace if possible, but…
我想尽可能避免 卷入后宫是非 但是…
now that I'm here, it can't be helped.
既然我进来了 想避也避不掉
Even though I had a pretty good life as an apothecary…
不过身为药师的我 在这儿的生活还算不错
The rear palace is an all-female area for giving birth to the emperor's child.
后宫住的全是女性 她们负责给皇帝生孩子
Men are strictly forbidden from entering this area.
这儿严格禁止男性出入
The only people who can enter here are high nobility and their blood relations.
只有贵族和他们的血亲 才能够进来这儿
Other than that, only eunuchs, or "former men"
除此之外 就只有失去“宝贝”的
who've lost their "precious parts" can enter.
宦官 又称“前男人”能够进入
All the consorts and palace women total 2,000.
所有的嫔妃和宫女 加起来总共有两千人
Along with the 1,000 eunuchs, it is a large living area.
另外还有一千名宦官 这个区域占地极广
Unlike the high, mid and low-ranking consorts,
与上级妃、中级妃、下级妃不一样
us maidservants doing menial tasks
我们这些负责杂务的婢女
can lose our lives at any moment.
随时有可能小命不保
SEVENTEEN
（壹七）
Next up is the shut-in low-ranking consort.
在我们之上的是被关起来的下级妃
At least we get paid a salary.
至少我们有薪俸
Hey, Maomao!
嘿 猫猫
Do you know which room this tag is for?
你知道这个牌子 指的是哪一个房间吗？
This is Wisteria Nine, so it's over there.
这是紫藤九号房 在那儿
Thank you!
谢谢
There are many maidservants who can't read.
有很多不识字的婢女
Before working at the rear palace,
在进入后宫工作之前
we are trained strictly in basic manners,
我们会接受严格的礼仪训练
but it's different with reading and writing.
但那跟阅读和书写不同
Even if you got higher salaries for your literacy,
尽管识字可以得到比较高的薪俸
the kidnappers would just take a higher portion of your pay.
但也只是被人口贩子 拿走更高的比例而已
But there are rare cases
但婢女被拔擢为
where maidservants are promoted to low-ranking consorts.
下级妃是极为罕见的事
Simply put…
简单来说吧…
it's looks.
就是外表
Freckles, flat chest.
雀斑、平胸
A figure with no curves.
一个毫无曲线的胴体
So it has nothing to do with me.
所以那跟我一点关系都没有
If I stand out too much, my life could be put at risk.
如果我太显眼 我的生命就会有危险
I'd rather stay like this.
我宁愿维持现状
If I shut up and work, I can leave after two years.
如果我闭嘴乖乖工作 两年后我就能离开了
I want to drink so bad!
我超想喝一杯的
-Hey, did you hear? -Huh?
-你听说了吗？ -什么？
There's apparently a really pretty eunuch in the central area.
京城有个长得非常漂亮的宦官
That's all everyone's talking about these days!
这些日子大家都在谈论这件事
I see.
是哦
If he's that beautiful, I'd love to see him once, don't you think?
如果他真有那么美 我还真想瞧瞧 你不这么认为吗？
A eunuch, huh?
宦官吗？
-She's lost a lot of weight. -Yeah.
-她瘦了好多 -对
Xiaoling…
小铃…
Unfortunately,
非常抱歉
the physician is fully occupied with the Eastern Palace.
太医全都在东宫忙着
I see.
是哦
They're just three months and six months old, right?
他们分别只有 三个月和六个月大 对吧？
Yes, both the Eastern Palace and Princess Lingli.
对 是东宫和铃丽公主
Do you think it's a curse, like they say?
你觉得就跟大家说的一样 是个诅咒吗？
What's this about?
你说什么？
You don't know, Maomao?
猫猫 你不知道这件事？
The entire rear palace is talking about this!
整个后宫都在谈论这件事
About the serial deaths of the heirs in the rear palace!
有关后宫妃子生下的储君 接连死亡的事件
All three of the Emperor's children got
皇帝的三个孩子从出生之后
gradually weaker after their births and died!
变得愈来愈虚弱 最后全都死掉了
It's strange, right?
不觉得很奇怪吗？
All three babies?
三个孩子全死了？
It looks like the same thing is happening now.
这次又发生一样的事了
The baby is sick?
婴儿生病了？
Exactly! So this time, there are doctors in both Lady Gyokuyou
没错！所以这一次玉叶娘娘
and Lady Lihua's residences!
和梨花娘娘的住处都有太医随伺在侧
The current emperor has no empress,
皇帝目前还没有立皇后
so Lady Lihua, who gave birth to the Eastern Palace will be empress!
所以生下东宫太子的梨花娘娘 就会是皇后
That's obvious.
那是想当然尔
If the emperor has no empress, the consort with the Eastern Palace,
如果皇帝没有皇后 东宫的妃子
Consort Lihua, is at the top of the rear palace.
梨花妃就会是后宫最有势力的人
But it's rumored that the emperor's favorite
但谣传皇上最爱的妃子是
is Lady Gyokuyou.
玉叶娘娘
People say that might have something to do with all this.
大家都说一切可能都与这些有关
A political power struggle, huh?
权力斗争 是吗？
I wonder if Lady Lihua's condition is more serious.
不晓得梨花娘娘的状况 是不是比较严重
I hear the doctor is by her side day and night.
我听说太医日夜守在她身边
Lady Lihua is unwell as well?
梨花娘娘也不舒服吗？
Yes. Both mother and child.
对 母子都有状况
I heard they have headaches, stomachaches, and nausea as well.
我听说他们会头痛、胃痛和恶心
Headaches, stomachaches, and nausea…
头痛、胃痛和恶心…
I knew it! It's definitely a curse!
我就知道！一定是诅咒！
-A curse? You've got to be joking. -What?
-什么诅咒 真无聊 -什么？
Headaches, stomachaches, and nausea…
头痛、胃痛和恶心…
Could murder by poison be a possibility?
有可能是毒杀吗？
No. If they want the throne, there's no reason for the princess to be targeted.
不对 如果他们想要的是王位 就没必要把公主当成目标
It's highly unlikely they were poisoned.
她们被毒杀的可能性微乎其微
It could be an illness, or…
可能是生病或是…
Could it be in their blood?
会是在血液里吗？
Why am I getting so serious over rumors?
我干嘛对谣言这么认真？
These are just speculations.
这些都只是揣测而已
Just speculation. However…
只是推测 然而…
I can check it out for a little bit.
稍微确认看看好了
As expected of a building where the high-ranking consorts live,
上级妃的住处就跟预期中一样
even a single pillar is more sophisticated
就连一根梁柱都比我们住的
than the building we live in.
整栋屋子都来得精致
It's your fault!
都是你的错
Lady Gyokuyou!
玉叶娘娘
Because you gave birth to a girl,
因为你生的是女儿
you intend to curse my son to death!
所以你企图诅咒我的儿子夭折
You know that that's impossible.
你也知道那是不可能的
Xiaoling is suffering just as much as your son.
小铃跟你的儿子一样痛苦
Lady Lihua is furious.
梨花娘娘气疯了
How unfortunate for Lady Gyokuyou.
玉叶娘娘也真倒霉
Sir Jinshi….
壬氏大人…
That's why I want you to examine my daughter as well.
所以我希望你也能检查我的女儿
Yes, but… Well…
对 但是…这个嘛…
Is that flustered eunuch in the middle, the physician?
那位夹在中间 无所适从的宦官是医官吗？
That quack doctor, is he stupid?
那个蒙古大夫 他傻了吗？
He spends all that time with the two consorts, and he really hasn't realized?
整天陪在两位娘娘身边 他真的还搞不清楚状况吗？
Or… could it be, he doesn't even know?
还是…有可能他根本就不知道？
Deaths of infants. Headache, stomachache, and nausea.
婴儿夭折、头痛、胃痛和恶心…
And even more, the haggard state of Lady Lihua.
不只这样 梨花娘娘也面容憔悴
This isn't a curse at all.
这果然与诅咒完全无关
The problem is how to tell them.
问题是 我该如何告诉他们？
If I can find something to write with…
如果我能找到书写用具…
Not a month had passed when the news about
还不到一个月
the Eastern Palace's death got around.
东宫去世的消息就传开了
It looks like you want to ask me something.
看来你有事想问我…
This is…
这是…
It was the day I visited the Crystal Pavilion
是我造访水晶宫那天
to ask for my daughter to be examined.
要求太医给我女儿做检查
This was placed by my window after that.
这是在那之后放在我的窗口上的
It was tied to this branch.
跟这根花枝绑在一起
A rhododendron?
杜鹃花？
"The powder is poison. Don't let the baby touch it.
“白粉有毒 别让婴儿接触到
Ignorance is sin."
无知是一种罪”
A court physician wouldn't leave such a cryptic message.
太医不可能留下这种神秘讯息
Yes, it looks like he never figured out how to treat the Eastern Palace.
对 看来他到最后都 还没想出该如何治疗东宫
Who wrote this letter?
这封信是谁写的？
I want you to find that out for me.
我希望你替我查出来
Now that I think about it, that time…
现在回想起来 那个时候…
If I can find something to write with…
如果我能找到书写用具…
Understood.
明白了
Could I keep this with me for a little while?
这个可以由我暂时保管吗？
The Emperor is cherishing the princess who survived,
皇上很疼惜存活下来的公主
so he's been visiting Lady Gyokuyou often.
所以更常去探望玉叶娘娘了
What about Lady Lihua?
梨花娘娘怎么样了？
I don't hear about that at all.
我完全没有听说有关她的消息
How convenient for him, huh?
也太便宜他了吧？
Oh, I finally found you!
我终于找到你了
You're to head to the Matron of the Serving Women's office right away.
你立刻前往宫官长房间
What?
什么？
You've been summoned?
你被传召了？
I wonder what this is about.
不晓得会是什么
All right, everybody who gathered here should enter.
好的 在这儿集合的人全都进去吧
Maidservants being summoned by a higher-up?
婢女被上级传召？
I have a bad feeling about this.
我有不好的预感
Are they just short on staff?
是人手不足吗？
Sorry to call you all like this.
抱歉 让各位特地跑来
Who is this bossy palace woman?
这位威严的宫女是谁啊？
I'm the manager of the rear palace, Jinshi.
我是主管后宫的壬氏
He's a man?
他是个男的？
I guess the "really pretty eunuch" Xiaolan mentioned was this guy.
我猜小兰说的那个 “很美的宦官”就是他了吧
What a waste for him
太可惜了吧
to be this beautiful and not be able to have children.
容貌如此动人 却不能够生小孩
THE FRECKLE WOMAN OVER THERE, YOU'RE STAYING WITH ME.
什么？
Freckle… Woman…
雀斑…女子
Oh, shit!
可恶
We're done for today. Go back to your rooms.
今天就到这里 你们可以回房了
Huh? What's going on?
什么？这是怎么回事？
Did I make some big mistake that got his attention?
我犯下了什么大错让他注意到了吗？
Could it be the letter from that time…
会是那时写的那封信吗？
I see! I'm the only maidservant here that can read.
我知道了！我是这儿唯一识字的婢女
He wrote that sentence to figure that out!
他写下这句话就是为了弄清楚这一点
Shit, I have to run…
可恶 我该走了…
You can't run. I told you, you're staying.
你不能走 你得留下来
Shut up and come with me.
闭上嘴巴 跟我走
I got played…
我被耍了…
This is strange.
很奇怪
I looked at my records and it said you can't read.
我看了我的纪录 上面写着你不识字
Yes, I was born of low class.
对 我是贱民出身
This must be some sort of mistake.
一定是哪里出错了
Why would I tell you?
我为什么要告诉你？
The world is easier to get around if you pretend to know nothing.
装聋作哑比较容易 在这个世界上存活下来
Anyways, how did this man find out about my letter?
再说 这个人 是如何发现我写的那封信？
I was careful of my surroundings!
我明明对周遭状况很小心翼翼
Why is he so suspicious?
他为何如此多疑？
He has way too much time on his hands!
况且他也太闲了吧
-Come in. -Excuse me.
-请进 -打扰了
What will they yell at me for?
他们会为了什么事臭骂我？
I hope I can make it out alive…
希望我能活着离开这儿…
I have come with the girl.
我把那位女子给带来了
Come in.
进来吧
I'm sorry for the trouble.
抱歉 麻烦你了
I'm so glad…
太好了…
So you are…
就是你…
You've saved my Lingli's life.
你救了我的铃丽一命
Thank you.
谢谢你
I'm not of a position for you to do such things!
小的地位卑贱 承受不起娘娘如此多礼
No. I can't thank you enough.
不 我对你实在感激不尽
My child owes you her life.
你是我的孩子的救命恩人
You're mistaking me for someone else.
娘娘是不是认错人了？
You've probably made a mistake.
娘娘应该是搞错了
I'd hate to get beheaded for contradicting her,
我万万不想因为否定她而被砍头
but I don't want to get involved!
但我实在不愿意牵扯其中
I have something from Consort Gyokuyou.
其实玉叶妃给了我一个东西
You know that this fabric is used in the uniform of maidservants, right?
你知道这块布是婢女制服的衣料吧？
I guess it looks similar…
看起来是很像啦…
Yes, it's used by maidservants in Wardrobe Service.
对 这是尚服婢女会用到的布料
For example, a laundry girl like you…
例如 像你这种洗衣婢女…
Maybe you ripped off a hem from your skirt.
你的裙摆不会刚好破了吧？
He even knew about that?
他连这个都知道？
Tell us.
说明一下吧
Why did you place a rhododendron branch by the window?
你为什么在窗口留下这根杜鹃花枝？
Because I found out about the truth behind the incidents.
因为我发现了这些意外的真相
It was caused by the face powder.
是白粉造成的
In the pleasure district where I grew up,
在我从小长大的花街
there were many courtesans who used expensive powder.
许多青楼女子都会用昂贵的白粉
Most of these women
她们大部分
were consumed by the poison contained in the powder
都被白粉里的毒侵害了
and lost their lives.
因此丧命
They weighed their lives against beauty,
她们拿性命换取美丽的容颜
and ended up losing both.
到最后两个都得不到
I was an apothecary,
我是个药师
so I know a lot about poison.
我认得很多有毒之物
That face powder…
那个白粉…
This was used by my child's wet nurse.
这是我孩子的奶娘在用的
She said the white of this powder stood out the most,
她说这款白粉的颜色最明亮
so she liked using this.
所以她很爱用
The wet nurse was also ill, so I placed her on leave.
奶娘也病了 所以我让她暂时不用过来
I gave her plenty of money as well.
我给她很多银子
I see.
这样啊
Ignorance is sin.
无知是一种罪
I should've kept a closer watch on what my child puts in her mouth.
我应该更加注意 我孩子吃进嘴里的东西
I should have as well.
我也是
If we had realized this earlier,
如果我们早点发现这件事
we could've saved many lives. Even the Eastern Palace…
就能够救活更多人命 甚至连东宫…
After finding this letter,
发现这封信之后
I told Consort Lihua about the powder as well, but…
我也把白粉的事告诉梨花妃了
She wouldn't listen to anything I had to say.
我说的话她都听不进去
So…
所以…
What should I do?
我该怎么办？
Starting today, you will be my attendant!
从今天开始 你就是我的贴身下人
What?
什么？
What Maomao can't hold back
猫猫实在控制不住
is her curiosity and her appetite for knowledge.
她的好奇心和求知欲
That, and a little bit of a sense of justice…
和一丝丝的正义感…
Shit, shit, shit!
糟了…
If I had just stayed put and worked.
如果我乖乖地安静做事
-I could've… -Welcome back, Maomao!
-我就不会… -你回来啦 猫猫
How did it go?
结果怎么样？
This is how Maomao became the lady-in-waiting for
这就是猫猫成为皇上宠妃
the Emperor's beloved Consort Gyokuyou.
玉叶妃的贴身下人的经过
In other words, she got a promotion!
也就是说 她晋升了
LI
（荔）
Hey!
喂
This is poison!
这有毒！
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集预告）
Next episode, "Chilly Apothecary."
下一集 《冷漠的药师》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：欧德慧